If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at new research
about the efficacy of supplements
in preventing Alzheimer's disease.
Oxidative stress
from free radicals
is the one of the pathways
implicated in the development
and deterioration
of Alzheimer's brains,
given the evidence of excess
oxidative DNA damage on autopsy.
So, what about trying
an antioxidant?
Vitamin E levels
tend to be lower
in the bloodstreams of those
with cognitive impairment
or dementia,
but which came first?
Maybe Alzheimer's disease
led to poor eating,
rather than poor eating
leading to Alzheimer's disease.
Greater vitamin E intake
from foods
is clearly associated
with a lower risk
of developing Alzheimer's,
but greater vitamin E intake
from supplements is not.
But, that didn't stop
researchers
from including a vitamin E arm
in the largest primary
prevention study
of Alzheimer's disease to date.
The Prevention
of Alzheimer's Disease
by Vitamin E and Selenium trial
randomized more than
7500 older men
to take vitamin E, selenium,
both, or neither-just placebos-
for five years.
To quote from the conclusion:
"Neither supplement
prevented dementia."
A separate long-term vitamin E
supplementation trial
of older women similarly found
no protection
against cognitive decline.
Neither did vitamin E
appear to benefit those
with mild cognitive impairment,
but the trials on Alzheimer's
patients themselves
started to get more interesting.
The first trial,
published in the New England
Journal of Medicine,
randomized more than 150
Alzheimer's patients
to vitamin E or placebo
to see if vitamin E could slow
the progression of the disease.
The primary outcome
was the number of days
until of one of any
of the following happened:
death, institutionalization,
loss of the ability
to perform basic activities
of daily living,
or sliding into severe dementia,
where you suffer
a complete loss
of sense of time or place.
On first analysis,
vitamin E flopped:
no significant slowing
of progression.
Digging deeper,
the researchers realized
that despite
the random allotment,
the placebo group
just by chance
ended up with patients
with milder disease.
After taking that into account,
the difference in outcomes
between the vitamin E
and placebo groups
widened substantially.
Now, this kind of
unplanned post-hoc analysis
is heavily frowned upon,
but the effect
seemed so sizable
they went ahead
and published it.
In the placebo group,
the adjusted time to death
or loss of independence
was 440 days,
but in the vitamin E group,
after the baseline cognition
was normalized,
it was 670 days,
more than seven months later.
However,
given the unorthodox analysis,
the scientific world waited
for the study to be replicated.
And here we go:
more than 600 patients
with mild to moderate
Alzheimer's disease
were subsequently randomized
to vitamin E supplements,
the drug memantine, both,
or neither (just placebos)
for two years.
Although there was no slowing
of cognitive decline
after adjusting
for multiple comparisons,
there was a slowing
of functional decline,
in terms of managing
daily activities
like bathing or dressing.
The vitamin E group
appeared to only suffer
about 1.5 years
of functional deterioration
in the two years' time,
resulting in approximately
two hours less caregiver time
required each day
compared to the drug group.
If those were the only two
clinical vitamin E trials,
I would give vitamin E
serious consideration
for those
with Alzheimer's disease.
But, there's a third,
a six-month trial,
that suggested vitamin E
may be detrimental
to cognition
in some Alzheimer's patients.
Obviously, more research
needs to be done.
I'll cover other antioxidants
that have been put to the test,
including vitamin C,
beta carotene,
Centrum multivitamin,
and the minerals
zinc and calcium.
Alzheimer's patients have
significantly lower blood levels
of 8 out of 10 antioxidants
investigated,
though, of course,
this could just be a consequence
of demented individuals
eating diets
poor in fruits and vegetables.
When put to the test,
the PREADViSE study
found no benefit
for vitamin E or selenium
in terms of
preventing dementia.
What about other antioxidants?
In the Harvard Physician's
Health Study,
nearly 6,000 older men
were randomized
to beta carotene or placebo.
No difference was found
after three years,
but after 11 years,
those unknowingly taking
the equivalent
of 3/4 cup (150 g)
of sweet potato
worth of beta carotene a day
had slightly
yet significantly better
overall cognitive performance.
A similar study of older women
found no cognitive benefit
over a period of nine years.
Maybe they just didn't wait
long enough?
Vitamin E and C
were also tested.
Vitamin E similarly flopped
throughout and so did vitamin C,
up until the last cognitive
assessment at around year 9
where the vitamin C group
appeared to pull ahead.
However, two trials of
a combination of vitamin C, E,
and beta carotene together
versus placebo,
one randomizing
1,500 older patients
for seven years,
and another truly massive one
randomizing more than
20,000 adults for five years,
both failed to show
any cognitive benefit
for the antioxidant cocktail.
What about a multivitamin?
The Physician's Health Study
also tested
taking the daily
multivitamin/multimineral
supplement Centrum Silver
for 12 years.
Compared to those instead
randomized to a placebo,
the Centrum group experienced
no cognitive benefit.
Souvenaid is a nutritional drink
containing a patented
formulation of nutrients,
branded as Fortasyn Connect,
specifically designed to help
in Alzheimer's disease.
Unfortunately,
it doesn't work.
There have been three
randomized controlled trials
enrolling more
than a thousand people,
and those taking Souvenaid
were no less likely
to develop dementia
in the first place,
and probably it has
little or no effect
on measures of memory
or other thinking skills
in both those
with mild cognitive impairment
or Alzheimer's disease.
In terms of specific minerals
other than the failed selenium,
zinc has similarly flopped
to improve overall cognition
over months or years
of supplementation,
and it's possible
calcium supplements
could make things worse.
Cross-sectionally,
those taking calcium
have more "hyperintensity"
brain lesions on MRI
(shown here in red, denoting
evidence of mini-strokes)
and longitudinally over time,
women taking
calcium supplements
appear to have twice the odds
of developing dementia.
The Women's Health Initiative
should have been able
to settle the question
once and for all.
Thousands of older women
were randomized
to calcium supplements
(plus vitamin D)
or placebo
for about eight years.
Thankfully, there was
no difference in the risk
of developing cognitive
impairment or dementia.
But that's what
was originally found
for heart attack
and stroke rates
before pre-existing
supplement use
was taken into account.
See, more than half of the women
were already taking
personal calcium supplements
before entering the study
and being randomized
to calcium or placebo.
You can imagine how this
could muddy the results.
If you just look at the women
who weren't
on calcium beforehand,
starting calcium resulted
in a significant increase
in the risk
of cardiovascular events,
consistent with a meta-analysis
of calcium trials
showing a 15 percent increase
in heart attacks or strokes
among those randomized
to calcium supplements
over placebo.
Unfortunately,
such a reanalysis
has yet to be performed
on the dementia data.
The bottom line is that vitamin
and mineral supplements
probably aren't going to help
prevent dementia or treat it,
but there are tons
of other things we can do.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.